Guide to the Robert Steck Photograph Collection ALBA.PHOTO.104
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robert Steck Photographs
1937-1996
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Steck, Robert
ALBA.PHOTO.104
1.75 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Robert Steck (1912-), actor and social activist, sailed to Europe to volunteer for service in the Spanish Civil War with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in January 1937. In the following months, Steck served in the International Brigades with the First Regiment de Tren, where he was made political commissar; worked with British writer Ralph Bates, putting out the magazine Volunteer for Liberty; headed the Tarazona Base Cultural Commission, adapting his theater experience to the political and social realities of the war and creating skits performed off the back of trucks (known as "Buffoons on Trucks"); and was rifleman, runner and battalion scout for the Third Lincoln company. This collection includes images acquired by Steck in the course of his service in Spain and images of Steck, and others, from before and after the Spanish Civil War. The collection contains non-combat photographs of the members of the First Regiment de Tren, images of Carl Geiser in Spain after the Civil War and of Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in a solidarity parade held in the United States and one image of the "Night of Stars," a New York City benefit for the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. The collection also includes portraits of Steck, images of Steck with his public school pupils and one image of Steck attending a picket and rally in Puerto Rico.
Approximately 730 black and white prints sized from 1 ½ x 1 ½ to 3 x 5 inches; 55 black and white contact sheets sized 8 x 10 inches; 78 black and white negatives sized from 2 1/8 x 2 ¼ to 2 ¼ x 4 inches; 48 35mm color slides, 3 35mm black and white slides.
Provenance
The bulk of material contained in the Robert Steck Photograph Collection was donated to the Tamiment Library by Robert Steck in 1979. The remaining Steck photographs were donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Robert Steck between 1979 and 1998. This portion of the collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The images in the Steck Photograph collection were separated from the Steck manuscript material at the time of processing.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Robert Steck, actor and social activist, sailed to Europe to volunteer for service in the Spanish Civil War with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in January 1937. In the following months Steck served in the International Brigades with the First Regiment de Tren, where he was appointed political commissar; worked with British writer Ralph Bates, putting out the magazine Volunteer for Liberty; headed the Tarazona Base Cultural Commission, adapting his theater experience to the political and social realities of the war and creating skits performed off the back of trucks (known as "Buffoons on Trucks"); and was rifleman, runner and battalion scout for the Third Lincoln Company. The photo collection reflects the range of Steck's progressive activities and concerns, including his long association with the communal adult camp, Camp Unity. This collection includes images acquired by Steck in the course of his service as a volunteer in Spain and images of Steck, and others, from before and after the Spanish Civil War. ( For further biographical information on Robert Steck see the Guide to the Robert Steck Papers, ALBA 104.)
Scope and Content Note
Series I, Subseries A: Spanish Civil War Photographs. The collection contains approximately 80 images including non-combat photographs of the members of the First Regiment de Tren (Robert English, Ernie Parlour, and William Sennett)-with one image showing Ralph Bates addressing the First Regiment; images of Carl Geiser in Spain after the Civil War and of Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in a solidarity parade held in the United States; and one image of the "Night of Stars," a New York City benefit for the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. The collection includes portraits of Steck, images of Steck with his public school pupils, in Spain addressing the First Regiment de Tren, in Spain with Charles Hall and Saul Wellman (Madrid, 1996) and one image of Steck relaxing after attending a picket line and rally in Puerto Rico. There are four images of prisoner of war Sol Leiserowitz with his family and friends in the United States, one image of Leiserowitz' mother and one of his father. Subseries A contains photocopies of contact sheets with images taken by the International Brigade's photographic unit led by Harry Randall. The contact sheets were removed and the images with Randall numbers were placed in ALBA Photo #11.
Series I, Subseries B: Camp Photographs. The collection contains approximately 650 images relating to Steck's experience at Camp Calumet, Camp Unity and other summer camps including landscapes, performances, portraits and sporting events. Eleven portraits taken at Camp Unity are attributed to Sylvia Chesteroff-Brown and 25 images of Paul Robeson at Camp Unity are attributed to Paul Bernstein. There is also one image of Pete Seeger performing at Camp Unity. The subseries contains 55 8 x 10 contact sheets of Camp Calumet with approximately 30 images per sheet.
Series III. Negatives and Slides. The collection contains 81 black and white negatives and 51 slides. The negatives include 78 images of Camp Calumet on 26 negative strips (measuring 3/8 x 7 ½ inches and containing three images per strip), two images of unidentified volunteers in Spain and one image of children in a classroom at Smith High School [?]. The slides include 48 color slides and three black and white slides. The color slides include 25 images of Camp Unity and 17 images of Camp Calumet, four images of San Pedro de Cardenas in Burgos, Spain (the location of a prisoner of war camp) and two images of Steck on vacation in China. The three black and white slides include two images of James Philips Lardner and one image of Steck shaving in Spain during the Civil War. None of the negatives or slides matches the prints.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic.The photographic prints are identified by four numbers separated by colons. The first number refers to the collection number, the second to the box number, the third to the folder number, and the fourth to the individual print. For example, the first print in this collection is labeled 104:1:1:1. The negatives and slides are numbered in a similar fashion and are contained in a separate box from the prints.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
I, Prints
II, Negatives and Slides
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robert Steck Audio Tape Collection, ALBA Audio 104
Robert Steck Manuscript Collection, ALBA 104
San Pedro de Cardenas (Spain); Black-and-white photographs.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Slides (photographs); Negatives (photographic); Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Theater and the war.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Portraits.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Pictorial works.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Drama.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Archives; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Geiser, Carl; Parlour, Ernie.; Sennett, William, 1914-; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Steck, Robert; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Historical Commission; Bates, Ralph, 1899-2000; English, Robert.
- Series I: Photographs
  - Subseries I:A: Spanish Civil War
    - Abraham Lincoln Brigade Benefit ("Night of Stars") with Fred Keating and Sunny Burns, Apr 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Anderson, [?]: Family, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - At the Front: Combat, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2a)
    - Bates, Ralph: Addressing First Regiment de Tren, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Behind the Lines: Daily Life of the Soldiers, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Blair, Harriet and Molly Parker: Snapshot, Los Angeles, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Blair, Harriet; Molly Parker and Max Parker: Snapshot, Los Angeles, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Brandt, Joe; George Watt; Milton Wolff and unidentified, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Briar, Morris [?] and unidentified: Machinegun Crew, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cameron, James and Jimmy Moon: Snapshot, Not in Spain, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Chase, Van Rensalaer: Snapshot, Not in Spain, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Contact Sheets: At the front, non-combat; Ernest Hemingway and unidentified individuals, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10a)
    - English, Robert and William Sennett: First Regiment de Tren, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Fajans, Irving: Group, Not in Spain, ca.1940 (Box 1, Folder 11a)
    - First Regiment de Tren: Celebration, Jul 4, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Gates, John; George Well and Four Unidentified Soldiers, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Geiser, Carl: Spain, Post-Civil War, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Geiser, Carl and Efrem Manzilla: Spain, Post-Civil War, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Geiser, Carl; Herman Streit and Georg Henke: Post-Civil War, Location Unknown, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Giler, Henry: Snapshot, Los Angeles, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Giler, Henry: Groups (with Gurko; Max Shufer; and Two Unidentified Soldiers), ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Grant, Walter: Portraits, Not in Spain, undated, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 18a)
    - Groups: Identified, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Groups: Unidentified, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 19a)
    - Individuals: Unidentified (Includes portrait of Martin [?]), undated, ca.1937-1938, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Jones, Tom: Portrait, Spain, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Keller, Fred: Snapshot, Los Angeles, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Kleemor, Harry and Mother, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Kleiman, Harry: Family and Anderson Family, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Kleiman, Harry: Groups (with Hy Wallach; with Doran, Opara, Anderson), 1930-1949 (Box 1, Folder 24a)
    - Kleiman, Tuva (Harry's Widow) and Fred Keller: Snapshot, Los Angeles, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Lamb, Leonard [?], ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Leiserowitz, Sol: Family and Friends, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Malkowski, Georg: Groups, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 27a)
    - New York University Volunteers: Leonard B. Levenson, Paul Sigal, Emanuel Mandel, Elkan Wendkos, ?; and Paul MachEachron (Oberlin College), at Azaila, Spain, Sep 1937 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Parker, Max with Molly Parker and Vicki Rhea: Snapshot, Los Angeles, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 28a)
    - Parlour, Ernie: First Regiment de Tren, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Prisoners of War: Spanish Civil War, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Rehil, Joseph Francis: Portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Rhea, Vicki (Al Ziegler's Niece): Snapshot, Los Angeles, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Robbins, Seymour "Rusty": Photographic Postcard, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 32a)
    - Rolfe, Edwin: Snapshot, Spain, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Ryan, Frank and John Robinson, Oct 1937 (Box 1, Folder 33a)
    - Snapshots: Spain, post-Civil War, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Stanley, Fred "Tex": Snapshot, Los Angeles, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 34a)
    - Steck, Robert: First Regiment de Tren, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Steck, Robert: Miscellaneous/Family and Friends, undated, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Steck, Robert: Picket and Rally in Puerto Rico, Feb 1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Steck, Robert: Portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Steck, Robert: World War II, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Steck, Robert with "Bob" [Ralph?] Fasanella, Matthew Irving Matison, Daiz Mal, Herbert Matthews, "Jim" [William?] Swan and Jack Yellin, Spain, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Steck, Robert with Charles Hall and Saul Wellman, Madrid, Nov 6, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Steck, Robert with Leo Markowitz and Murray Schwermer, Spain, Feb 1937 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Strike: Spain, post-Civil War, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Stuart, Yale, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Tisa, John, Apr 1938 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Office, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - VALB: Solidarity Parade, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Subseries I:B: Camp Photographs
    - Camp Calumet: Activities, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Camp Calumet: Brochure Photos, Postcards, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Camp Calumet: Contact Sheets (I), undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Camp Calumet: Contact Sheets (II), undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Camp Calumet: Groups, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Camp Calumet: Landscapes, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Camp Calumet: Nature, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Camp Calumet: Pets, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Camp Calumet: Portraits, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Camp Calumet: Realia, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Camp Calumet: Softball/Tennis, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Camp Calumet: Theater Productions, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Camp Calumet: Water Sports, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Camp Unity: Ephemera, undated (Box 2, Folder 9a)
    - Camp Unity: Exteriors/Landscapes, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Camp Unity: Exteriors/Landscapes (Oversize), undated (Box 3A, Folder 1)
    - Camp Unity: Performances, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Camp Unity: Performances (Oversize) (Box 3A, Folder 1)
    - Camp Unity: Portraits and Groups, 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Camp Unity: Portraits and Groups, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Camp Unity: Portraits and Groups, 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Camp Unity: Portraits and Groups, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Camp Unity: Portraits and Groups, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Camp Unity: Recreation, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Camp Unity: Recreation (Oversize), undated (Box 3A, Folder 2)
    - Camp Unity: Paul Robeson, Concert Site, Peekskill, N.Y., undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Camp Unity: Robeson, Paul, Visit, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Camp Unity: Seeger, Peter, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Pre-Camp Calumet, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Saroff, Sophie: 80th Birthday Dinner, Apr 4, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Camp Unity: Scrapbook Photocopies, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series II: Negatives and Slides
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Negatives, ca.1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Camp Calumet: Negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 1a)
  - Camp Calumet: Slides, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Camp Unity: Slides, 1940-1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Lardner, James Philips: Spain, Slides, ca.1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - San Pablo de Cardenas: Burgos, Spain, Slides, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Steck, Robert: China Trip, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Steck, Robert: Smith High School, Negative, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Steck, Robert: Spain, Civil War, Slide, ca.1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 8)